<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The proclamation and edict of the archbyshop, and prince elector of Culleyn. Declarynge his occasion and earnest intention, to bring in the free exercise of the preaching of the Gospel, and peace and lybertie to true Christian religion Proclaymed at Bon, in the yeare of our Lorde, 1583. Imprinted at Antwerp, in Tannets streete, at the signe of the Gylden Bible, by Paule Braeckvelt, 1583. With the consent and priuiledge of the lordes of of the cittie of Antwerp.</title>
            <author>Gebhard, Truchsess von Waldburg, Archbishop and Elector of Cologne, 1547-1601.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1583</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 13 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01568</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11694</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119709</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854916</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854916</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20374</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01568)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20374)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 568:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The proclamation and edict of the archbyshop, and prince elector of Culleyn. Declarynge his occasion and earnest intention, to bring in the free exercise of the preaching of the Gospel, and peace and lybertie to true Christian religion Proclaymed at Bon, in the yeare of our Lorde, 1583. Imprinted at Antwerp, in Tannets streete, at the signe of the Gylden Bible, by Paule Braeckvelt, 1583. With the consent and priuiledge of the lordes of of the cittie of Antwerp.</title>
                  <author>Gebhard, Truchsess von Waldburg, Archbishop and Elector of Cologne, 1547-1601.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Richard Iones and I. S[tell?],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>the .18. of March. 1583.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The Archbishop of Collen = Gebhard, Truchsess von Waldburg.</note>
                  <note>A different translation from STC 11693. Only the first part of that item.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A B³.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Celibacy --  Catholic Church --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20374:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20374:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Edict of the Archbyſhop, and Prince Elector of CVLLEYN.</p>
            <p>Declarynge his occaſion and earneſt intention, to bring in the free exerciſe of the preaching of the Goſpel, and peace and lybertie to true Chriſtian Religion.</p>
            <p>¶ Proclaymed at BON, in the yeare of our Lorde, 1583.</p>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at <hi>Antwerp,</hi> in <hi>Tanners</hi> ſtréete, at the Signe of the Gylden Bible, by PAVLE BRAECKVELT, 1583.</p>
            <p>With the conſent and Priuiledge of the the Lordes of the Cittie of Antwerp.</p>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at <hi>London,</hi> by <hi>Richard Iones</hi> and I.S. the .18. of March. 1583.</p>
            <p>¶ Aucthoriſed and allowed.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:20374:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20374:2"/>
            <argument>
               <p>The Copie out of the high Dutche.</p>
            </argument>
            <head>The Chriſtian E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict &amp; Proclamation, of the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop and Prince Elector of Cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leyn: concernyng his Princely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention to bring in the holy Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell. Geuen at BON, the .xvi. of Ianuarie. 1583.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E Gebhart</hi> by the grace of god elected, and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Archbyſhop of <hi>Culleyn,</hi> Archchauncellour of the holye Empire through all <hi>Italie,</hi> and Elector: Duke of <hi>Weſtphalen</hi> and <hi>Ingrene. &amp;c:</hi> do let and giue
<pb facs="tcp:20374:3"/> to witte and vnderſtande vnto all and ſinguler Archdeacons of our Iuriſdiction, Countrey ſtates, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arles, Knights, States and other perſons, ſubiectes vnto vs: and to all others that ſhall haue occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to vſe our grace and fauour, and to euery of them, ioyntly and ſeuerallie. That ſince we recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the ſtate &amp; place of our Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhopricke and Prince Electours Gouernment, wherin the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie God, by free and lawfull ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction hath placed vs, wee haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes acknowledged and at this preſent doe acknowledge that we are bounde to doe our duety and endeuoure, to maintayne and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende all ſuch as by God are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytted to our Princely Election and Archbyſhopricke, and lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe our common natiue Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey
<pb facs="tcp:20374:3"/> of the Dutch Nation: &amp; moſt ſpeciallye and aboue all other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectes to aduance &amp; ſet before our eyes the honour of God before all other matters, wherunto with al diligence and hartie affection wee are inclined.</p>
            <p>For aſmuch as moſt earneſt, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; hartie petition &amp; requeſt hath been lately made vnto vs by our Nobilitie &amp; knights, &amp; other Prouinces &amp; cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>treies in no ſmal nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, &amp; alſo by the letters of ſome great perſonages of high eſtate &amp; calling, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in the ſacred &amp; holy Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyre, to ſuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r, admit &amp; allow vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in al places of our Iuriſdiction &amp; auctorytie, the publike &amp; ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preaching of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Goſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pell, and vſe &amp; adminiſtration of the holy Sacraments, accordyng to the ſacred worde and Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
<pb facs="tcp:20374:4"/> of God, and the Confeſſion of <hi>Auſpurghe,</hi> grounded vppon the ſame holy Scriptures. And theruppon, conſideryng the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtyng &amp; vnchangeable wyll of God, that it is our duties to heare his Sonne, and earneſtlye to do his wyll. And that all Princes and Gouernours of the worlde, ought too cauſe the Gates to bee ſette wide open, for the Kyng of Glory, and to let all people to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in vnto him. Wherunto wee haue ſpeciall Commaundement from God in our vocation, and do feele in our conſcience, how gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly in the day of iudgment, we ſhall yeeld accompt and make an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer before God for all our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſhuttyng vp the waye of ſaluation to our leage people.</p>
            <p>And acknowledgyng and confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng
<pb facs="tcp:20374:4"/> our ſelues to bee bounde to feare God, from the bottom of our heartes, and obedientlie to follow his Commaundements, and that hee is a mightie and iuſte Iudge, and conſuming fire, whoſe feare wee oughte continuallie to ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes. And for that wee being Chriſtian ſuperior, thought it our duetie before God, no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to refuſe to accompliſhe the earneſte and humble petition and ſuite, of our Nobilitie and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes. Wee therefore by the aduiſe of our Lordes and frendes, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter mature conſultation therupon had and taken, doe graunte and permit vnto all perſons, of what eſtate, degree, or callinge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oeuer they bee, eyther ſubiecte vnto our Aucthority, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rends, and bearing good wil to our Archbiſhopprick,
<pb facs="tcp:20374:5"/> the Chriſtian lybertie of their con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſciences, by Gods worde allowed. And do wyll, conſent, graunt and confirme vnto them by vertue of theſe Preſentes, that if any of the Subiectes or Inhabitauntes of any Cytie, Towne or place of our Iuriſdiction, ſhall by any of our Officers, Commiſſioners, Mage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates or miniſters, whatſoeuer, in or about maters of faith, religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or conſcience, be impriſoned, dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified, molleſted or troubled either in Honour, dignitie, Fame, Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, bodie or goodds, for Gods woorde, or follow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng the confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Auspurghe.</hi> That then eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of them ſhal bee freely cleared, ſet at liberty, and diſcharged from all impriſonment, loſſe, moleſtatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; trouble whatſoeuer, growinge for anie ſuch reſpect.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20374:5"/>
            <p>Alſo wee doe licenſe, graunte and confirme herewithall vnto our Prelates, Earles, Lordes, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitantes, Eſtates, Commons, Townes, and other Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations of people, of our prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Election and Archbyſhopricke, that they maye and ſhall, by war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rante hereof, haue full power and Authoritie, to exerciſe and put in vre, the free and open Exerciſe of the preachynge of the Goſpell, and the Adminiſtratyon and vſe of the holye Sacramentes, accordynge to the holye Scryptures of the Prophetes and Apoſtles, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greable to the Contentes and vſe of the confeſſion of <hi>Aurpurghe,</hi> therevppon grounded, without moleſtation of our Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners, Iuſtyces and Offycers, or anye
<pb facs="tcp:20374:6"/> eyther of our Iuriſdiction, whome wee doe meane to defende &amp; aſſiſt with the helpe of the Almightie God: truſting alſo vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the mighty power of God, that he will merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie aſſiſt and fauour vs in our ſo godly an enterpriſe and meaning, and be our defence agaynſt all the Gates of Hell, to the maintenance of his glorie and holie worde.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, wee doe hereby de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare and proteſte before the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God, who is the chiefe truth, and a knower of the ſecrets of all mens heartes, that wee are not mooued and ledde to this our chriſtian intentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, through world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wiſedome, deſire of Honour, or anie other wordly reſpect: neyther herein do ſeeke the profit, honour, dignitie, or eſtimation of our ſelfe,
<pb facs="tcp:20374:6"/> but onelye doe ſeeke to aduaunce the honour and glorie of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, and to ſet foorth his holye woorde. And our intent and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning herein, is chiefly to ſeeke the proſperitye and Saluation of our Subiectes, whome God hath com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mitted to our charge.</p>
            <p>Let no man therefore imagine or thinke, that wee are inclined to nouelties or troubles. For oure intente and deſyre is, to ſee good Chriſtian orders maynteined and kepte with peace and quyetnes, in Churches and Schooles of mens heartes.</p>
            <p>And ſo wee are minded by the aduyſe &amp; counſayle of the States of our Countreys, and other our Lordes and frendes, to publiſhe &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:20374:7"/> ſet foorthe Chriſtyan Orders to bee obſerued and followed in all Churches and Schooles of oure Archbiſhopricke.</p>
            <p>In the meane tyme wee are aduyſed, to geue warnynge to all ſuche as intende to lyue after the woorde of GOD, and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of <hi>Auspurghe,</hi> to vſe and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue them ſelues with all reaſon and affectyon, as good Chriſtians oughte to doe. And wee requyre and praye them moſte hartilye, that no man molleſt, trouble, defy, blaſpheme or vexe one an other by woorde or deede. But that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerye of them behaue themſelues one towards an other peaceably and quyetlye in their conuerſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and dealynges. And to lyue and continue accordynge to the
<pb facs="tcp:20374:7"/> Eontentes of this oure preſente Edict.</p>
            <p>And as touchynge oure owne Perſon in this caſe. Whereas ac, cordynge to the Counſayle and appoyntmente of Almighty God, wee haue entered into the Holye State of Marryage, and that publiquelye, wherein no man is able iuſtlie to accuſe vs to haue doone the ſame agaynſte the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed Order, or that wee haue anye meanynge to ſeeke our pryuate aduauntage, or anye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other thynge preiudyciall to oure Archbyſhopricke, and Prynce E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectorſhyppe, or to appropryate the ſame in Succeſſyon and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ytaunce to oure Heyres: Wee therefore, doe make oppen and
<pb facs="tcp:20374:8"/> plaine Teſtimonie and Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by theſe preſents, by the high<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eſt trueth: (which is God Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie himſelfe) and hereby do proteſt that we haue no meaning or will, nor are in anie wyſe inclyned or bent, to bringe our Byſhoppricke, to the propryetie or poſſeſſyon of our Heyres, neyther to bringe in anie Noueltie or Alteration, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge to oure pryuate pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ytte or aduauncement. But doe hereby openlye publiſhe and declare, that a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ter our Deceaſe, our Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Chapyter of oure Cathedrall Churche of <hi>Culleyn,</hi> ſhall haue their free Libertye and Election lefte vnto them, and ſhall remaine in all reſpects, as in their auncient former eſtate.</p>
            <p>Alſo we are content, and giue
<pb facs="tcp:20374:8"/> our Commaundement touchinge the premiſſes to all and ſinguler Inhabitantes and Subiectes of our Archbyſſhopryke and Prince Electorſhip: that an orderly choice and free election may be made of a future ſupreme head, to gouerne them after our deceaſe or free re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation: yet neuertheleſſe, our meanynge is, that, whoſoeuer ſhall be in election to come to that ſucceſſion by an orderly choice &amp; free election, ſhall be no other but ſuch a one as is bounde vnto our ſaide Chapiter of our ſaide Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedrall Church, and a Lorde ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable, by th'ordinaunces of the ſame to come to that degree, and a man of our iuriſdiction, both o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient and fytte, and worthye in all reſpectes for the place when it ſhal fall vnto him: and otherwiſe,
<pb facs="tcp:20374:9"/> not to bee elected to ſuche prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by any meanes. And what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, ſuch perſon as ſhall be by ſuche orderly proceedinge, choice and free election of our worthye Chapiter of our ſaid Cathedrall Church, choſen and elected to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede after our ſayd deceaſe or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation. They ſhall acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge him for their future Lorde, any Lawe, Statute, Act, Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce, Edict, or Proclamation, made, ordained, or prouided, either by vs, or any other whatſoeuer he be, to the contrary of this our pub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyke declaration, in any wiſe not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtandyng: for we, all ſuch do now, &amp; alwayes wyl cancel, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nichilate and make of none effect.</p>
            <p>All the ſame premiſes, we wiſh to be done in the cheefeſt and beſt
<pb facs="tcp:20374:9"/> manner and forme that may bee, to thende the ſame may continue of the better force and effect: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, we will be obedient and lay to our helping hande, and therein wyll agree and conſent with our ſaid Chapiter &amp; inhabitants and confyrme the aforeſaid conditions with aſſurance therof, in ſuch ſort that no man ſhall haue iuſt cauſe to miſtruſt or conceaue any feare of vs, or of our Heyres or Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, wee wyll and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde all our Baylyffes, Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Offycers, Lieutennauntes, Gouernours, Cuſtomers, Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughmaiſters, Cytizens, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people, Miniſters and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes and whatſoeuer, vpon this our publique Edict and Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,
<pb facs="tcp:20374:10"/> with all their endeuour, to obſerue and performe the ſame: and to cauſe the ſame Edict and Proclamaiion to bee obeyed and maintayned from point to point:</p>
            <p>And alſo contrarye to the true meanynge thereof, not to encom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber or trouble, or ſuffer to bee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbred or troubled, any perſon or perfons of any degree, vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or calling whatſoeuer, vppon paine of our high diſpleaſure and indignation, &amp; greeuous puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be inflicted withall vpon the offenders, breakers or repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of this our preſent Edict and Proclamation: for ſuch is our ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and finall intent and wyll.</p>
            <p>In witneſſe wherof, we haue cauſed this our Proclamation to be openly printed and confirmed
<pb facs="tcp:20374:10"/> with our Seale, and that through al our Archbiſhoprick and Prince Electorſhip, to thend, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euery man ſhould haue knowledge thereof.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Giuen in our Citie of BON, <date>the .xvi. Day of Ianu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arie, in the yeare of the Computa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the byrth of our Lorde Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, 1583.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed at London by Richarde Iones: at the Signe of the <hi>Roſe</hi> and the <hi>Crowne,</hi> neere <hi>Holburne</hi> Bridge. 19. MARCH, 1583.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:20374:11"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of portrait of old man, forehead marked with astrological signs</figDesc>
                  <p>♈</p>
                  <p>♓</p>
                  <p>♂</p>
                  <p>
                     <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> ☉</p>
                  <p>♀</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20374:11"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
